Guide to the Richard St. John Papers, 1972-2020 SC.2020.03
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Richard St. John Papers
1972-2020
ULS Archives & Special Collections
St. John, Richard, 1952-
SC.2020.03
8 Linear Feet (4 record center boxes, 1 oversized box)
Richard St. John is a published writer of three collections of poetry, titled The Pure Inconstancy of Grace (2005), Each Perfected Name (2015),Book of Entangled Souls (2020), and one chapbook, titled Shrine (2011). The St. John Papers include drafts, manuscripts, newspaper clippings, photographs, audio material, and copies of his published works (with the exception of Book of Entagled Souls), including periodicals in which St. John's poetry has been featured.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acqusition Information
Gift of Richard St. John on June 25, 2020.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 9 series:
I. The Pure Inconstancy of Grace
II. Shrine
III. Each Perfected Name
VI. John the Baptist Series of Poems
V. Poetry experiments: inspired by current news and events
VI. Notebook experiments
VII. Poetry by decade
VIII. Poetry published in periodicals
IX. Audio-visual materials
Biography
Born in 1952 in Columbus, Ohio, Richard St. John is a poet and the author of two published volumes of poetry, titled The Pure Inconstancy of Grace (2005) and Each Perfected Name (2015), and one chapbook, titled Shrine (2011). St. John and his family moved to suburban Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, in 1955. Under the influence of a gifted middle and high school teacher, St. John became interested in poetry and, by the time of his 1970 graduation from high school, he was fully committed to becoming a poet. He attended Princeton University, graduating summa cum laude with a B.A. in English in 1974, and then went to the University of Virginia for his M.A. in English in 1975. It was during this time at U.VA that he became engaged to his longtime friend, Katherine "Kate" Mitchell, and after completing his degree, they married.
St. John considered teaching as a career, but following his graduation from college, he accepted a position at a Pittsburgh advertising agency, Creamer FSR, where he worked for four years. Wanting to commit himself to poetry more, he entered the nonprofit sector in 1981 and secured a half-time writing position with the Allegheny Conference on Community Development. In 1982, he accepted a full-time position at the Conference with a mix of writing and program responsibilities, including work in the organization's new program area of neighborhood development.
From 1984 through 1990, he worked with Oakland Planning and Development Corporation (OPDC) as Associate Director and then as Executive Director. While at OPDC, he completed a National Internship in Community Development through the Development Training Institute headquartered in Baltimore, Maryland. He continued working in neighborhood development as a real estate development consultant to a tenants' organization and subsequently, from 1992 to 2001, as Executive Director for the Community Design Center of Pittsburgh. Throughout this period, he also was active with a variety of nonprofit boards, commissions, and coalitions, including the Mayor's Zoning Advisory Group (as co-chair), Sustainable Pittsburgh, the Community Technical Assistance Center, the Working Group on Community Development, and others.
In the mid-1990s, in the hope of having a collection published, St. John began sending his book-length poetry manuscripts to publishers while continuing to work in the nonprofit sector. In 2001, St. John left the Community Design Center of Pittsburgh and accepted a mid-career Loeb Fellowship for independent study at Harvard University. Returning to Pittsburgh in 2002, he raised funds and initiated Conversations for Common Wealth (CCW), a program which used poetry and other materials to help diverse groups reflect on the ethical callings in their lives. He also assisted the Community House Literacy Center and Community House Presbyterian Church with various projects, including renovation of new space for both organizations.
In 2004, one of his manuscripts was selected as first runner-up for the T.S. Eliot Prize for Poetry, and one year later, Truman State University Press published that collection as The Pure Inconstancy of Grace. In 2007, at the conclusion of both CCW and Community House projects, he became Executive Director of Autumn House Press in Pittsburgh, a nationally respected nonprofit publisher of poetry, fiction and creative non-fiction. St. John left Autumn House Press to pursue conversations-related partnerships in 2011 and subsequently accepted a position as Executive Director for the Squirrel Hill Urban Coalition, retiring from that position in late 2014.
In the same decade, Finishing Line Press published his long poem as a chapbook, titled Shrine (2011), and Truman State University Press published his second full-length collection, titled Each Perfected Name (2015). Throughout his writing career, St. John was published in numerous newspapers and literary journals, such as The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, Pittsburgh City Paper, Carolina Quarterly, Sewanee Review, and The Fourth River. In addition, St. John has read his poetry at numerous cafés, universities, and events. St. John still continues to write and has completed a third full-length collection of poetry with the working title Book of Entangled Souls, which is scheduled for publication by Broadstone Books in 2022.
Scope and Content Notes
The St. John Papers contain written or typed drafts and manuscripts of St. John's poetry from the early 1970s to 2020, as well as correspondence, newspaper clippings, advertisements, books, and literary journals associated with St. John's poems. The collection includes multiple draft versions of the poems in St. John's three published volumes in addition to many drafts and largely unpublished works of poetry created throughout the decades. The correspondence highlights some conversations with other authors, editors, and friends about St. John's poetry. Photographs of St. John's trip to Walden Pond in Massachusetts are also available along with an audio recording of a radio show's poetry reading.
Related Material
Lawrence Lee Papers, 1920-1978, SC.1978.01, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Gerald Stern Papers, 1920-2012, SC.2007.04, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Liane Ellison Norman Papers, 1955-2008, AIS.2010.02, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Poetry -- Publishing; Poets, American -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Poets, American -- 20th century; Poetry; Manuscripts (Documents); Correspondence; Clippings (Information artifacts); Poetry; St. John, Richard, 1952-
- The Pure Inconstancy of Grace, 1975-2020; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains the published copy and drafts of St. John's collection of poetry, The Pure Inconstancy of Grace. Oversized materials that appear in this series can be found in Oversize 5.
  - Assortment of poetry reading advertisements, 2005-2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clarion Call newspaper, Vol 98, Ed 18 / UCONN poetry reading advertisement, 2006-2012 (Oversize 5, Folder 1)
  - The Pure Inconstancy of Grace advertisements, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Pure Inconstancy of Grace, published book, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Heidegger's Pear", 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Banding", 2001 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Praying in the Dark, Age 50", 2002-2004 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "All Saints Eve", 1997-2004 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Epiphany at the Dennis Public Dump", 1977-1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "J. Paul Getty at Forest Lawn", 1980-1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Two Stories", 2000 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "A Baptism", 1997 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "From the Plate", 1998-2004 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Photographs, Circa the Present", 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Circling Walden Pond", 2000-2004 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "The Darkened Mosaic", 1995-2004 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "L'Anima Semplicetta," correspondences about poem, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "The Way the Spheres Must Move", 1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "A Largo", 1997 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "The Bird in Our Garage", 1981-1997 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Walking with the Lady with Three Dogs", 1991-1997 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "The Amazing Wireless Receiver", 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Nighthawks", 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "The Sainthood of St. Julian", 1981 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "This Light," correspondence about this poem, 1996-2004 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "For a Friend Turning Thirty", 1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "The Grecian Urn Responds", 2001 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Upstate New York, in Difficult Times", 1975-2020 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "Mediation for a Wedding", 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "The Chokeberry and the Mower—A Valedictorian", 1997 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "All Souls Fight", 2001 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "Annunciations", 2000 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "Christmas Requiem", 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "Walking With. Keeping On.," table of contents, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - "Eat, Choose," draft manuscript, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - "The Pure Inconstancy of Grace," draft manuscript, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "Kant's Three Questions," draft manuscript and correspondences, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Shrine, 2004-2011; II.
  This series contains the published copy and drafts of St. John's long poem published as a chapbook, titleed Shrine.
  - Shrine, published poetry book, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, published excerpt from Shrine, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - "Poem for a Consecration", 2004 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - "Shrine," early draft, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - "Shrine, alternative title: Learning the Sign for Leaf," correspondences about poem, 2005-2010 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - "Shrine" drafts, 2005-2010 (Box 1, Folder 42-45)
- Each Perfected Name, 1993-2015; III.
  This series contains the published copy and drafts of St. John's collection of poetry, Each Perfected Name.
  - Each Perfected Name, shrink-wrapped copy, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Manuscript copy of Each Perfected Name, draft, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - "Metaphysics of Thrushes", 2004 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - "Second Birth," early drafts, 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - "The Sparrows of Bahrain", 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - "Fireflies", 2005-2011 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - "Helsinki Accord", 1994-2011 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - "Autumn Comes to Ithaka", 2011 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - "The Moon, the Stars, the Missing Mass", 2006-2009 (Box 1, Folder 54-56)
  - "Sparrow in the Supermarket", 2004 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - "The Virtue That Makes All Others Possible", 2001-2007 (Box 1, Folder 58-59)
  - "Irrefutable Logic of the Tiles", 2008 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - "Eclipse", 2007-2009 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Vita Nuova", 2007-2011 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Succinct Meditations on Fire", 2009 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "LOST TURTLE", 2008 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Dog Days—A Conversation", 2009 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "The Wolf at Gubbio", 2010-2012 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Prom Night", 2009 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Inner Ear", 2013 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "December, New Millennium", 2012-2013 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - "Abhorrent Things", 2011 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Learning with the Lost", 2003 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "A Blessing in Baltimore", 1993-2000 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Triple Fence at Friendship Park, California", 2013 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "Maria's Song", 2011 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "I Write to the G-20 Leaders in Advance of Their Pittsburgh Summit", 2009 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Reading Shaw's Play, St. Joan at the Solstice, on a Greyhound, Heading Home", 2008- 2009 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - "'The Garden Will Come to You' / A Conversation", 2007 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "Yet Another Resurrection Appearance", 2010 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "On Being Asked for a Poem that Embodies Non-Anthropocentric Spirituality", 2012 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "After Reading Amichai's Poem Called "Here" I Walk Past the Girls' Softball Practice", 2009 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - "Kant and His Manservant", 2002-2006 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "The Turning," early drafts, 2011-2012 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "All Hallows' Eve", 2011-2012 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Elegy with Braids and Tulips", 2003-2011 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - "Helen Elegy/Each Perfected Name", 2012-2013 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Each Perfected Name assorted advertisements, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - "Fireflies", 2011 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "Prom Night", 2009 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "Vita Nuova", 2008-2011 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - "Elegy with Braids and Tulips", 2006-2011 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "The Sparrows of Bahrain", 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - "The Wolf at Gubbio", 2010 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - "Maria's Song", 2011 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - "Autumn Comes to Ithaka", 2011 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - "Second Birth", 2010-2011 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- John the Baptist Series of Poems, 1997-2000; IV.
  This series contains a group of unpublished poems known as the "John the Baptist Series."
  - "A Preface: John the Baptist Series", 1999 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - "The Burial", 1998 -1999 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - "A Calling", 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - "The Dance", 1999 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - "Epilogue", 1998 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - "Magnificat", 1999 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - "Naming", 1999 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - "In the Wilderness", 1998 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - "Locusts (or) Honey", 1997-1999 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - "The Kingdom is Upon You", 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - "Two Shirts," correspondence about poem, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - "Winnow", 1999 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - "Series Notes", 1997-1999 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - "A New Gospel of St. John", 1999 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - "John the Baptist Series Draft with Preface", 1999 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Reference Materials, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - "In Prison", 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Poetry experiments: inspired by current news and events, 2007-2008; V.
  This series includes poetry drafts that all have newspaper clippings attached to them that relate to or are the inspiration for the subsequent poem.
  - "Brainy Parrot Dies", 2007 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - "New Bishop Faces Challenge of Shrinking Priesthood", 2007 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - "State to Close Mayview Hospital", 2007 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - "Wind-Power Guidelines Said to Harm Bats", 2007 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - "Bombing Toll in North Iraq May Reach 500", 2007 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - "Ex Transit Chief Sues for Pension", 2007 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - "Bush Warns Karzai to Be Wary of Iran", 2007 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - "190,000 Guns Go AWOL In Iraq", 2007 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - "Biggest Financial Rescue in the Country's History Sent to House Floor", 2008 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Untitled drafts, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - "Gay Episcopal Bishop Consecrated in New Hampshire", 2007 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Assorted newspaper articles and printed out news articles, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 66)
- Notebook experiments, 2017-2019; VI.
  This series includes poetry drafts of "unrhymed sonnets," as described by St. John.
  - "Night Class", 2017-2019 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - "Antidote", 2017 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - "Leech", 2017 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - "Lacunae", 2017 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - "Caliban", 2017 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - "Letters", 2017 (Box 2, Folder 72)
- Poetry by decade, 1972-2019; VII.
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes drafts, revisions, and notes related to the poetry that Richard St. John composed over a fifty-year time period. These drafts, referred to by the author as "discarded materials," are unpublished.
  - Poetry from the 1970s, 1972-1996; 1.
    This subseries contains early content and writings from St. John's time as an undergraduate student at Princeton and graduate student at the University of Virginia, including junior and senior theses, literary magazine publications, and collections of poetry. It also contains more drafts of poetry after his collegiate years. Some of the dates range to years outside of the 70s due to the author's later revision of the poems. Oversized materials that appear in this series can be found in Oversize 5. These drafts, referred to by the author as "discarded materials," are unpublished.
    - Gates, "Going to the Stables (For Barb, Mark, and Nathan)", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Rivanna, "On Graduating Empty-handed", 1975 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Nassau Lit, "On Graduating Empty-handed" "In the Image of God", 1974 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Poetry Reading advertisement, 1974 (Oversize 5, Folder 3)
    - Nassau Lit Special Edition, "To My Grandfather at the Piano" "From in the Safe", 1972 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - "A First Stroke," Junior Independent Work Collection, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - "Through a Glass Darkly," Senior Thesis & envelope containing grade, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - "The Chairman of the Board and the shade of Catherine the Great at Clairton Works (U.S. Steel Open House, June 26, 1976)" (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - "The Sub-Sub-Librarian Speaks", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - "Augustine at Matins", 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - "Like Dante, For Robert Lowell (1917-1977)" (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - "Selling an Old Washer at the Troy Hill Projects", 1978-1996 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - "Where are those nymphs?", 1978 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - "School Children at the Louisiana Capitol", 1978-1996 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - "Cattle on the Baton Rouge Levee", 1978 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - "Glass Elevator at the Peachtree Plaza", 1978 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - "Elegy on the Bayou", 1978 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - "Apotheosis of the Crawfish", 1978 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - "Standing by Andy Jackson in New Orleans", 1978 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - "Greeting Penelope", 1978-1996 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - "Wearing Our Gas Masks", 1978 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - "The Long Shower", 1978 (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - "Last Night in Sodom", 1978-1996 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - "The Marriages", 1973-1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "After the Flower Show", 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - "Epithalamion, For Herbert and Sue Martin", 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - "At St. Rosalia's Fair", 1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - "After a Presidential Speech", 1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "To a Friend, Moving Away", 1979-1996 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - "Family at Niagara Falls (Painting Concept by Jim Stein for "Man and His Environment" Show.)", 1978-1996 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Poetry from the 1980s, 1979-1997; 2.
    This subseries contains drafts of poetry dated in the 1980s. Some of the dates range to years outside of the 80s due to the author's later revision of the poems. These drafts, referred to by the author as "discarded materials," are unpublished.
    - "The Lost Art", 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - "Houses on a Hill", 1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - "Friday Night Softball", 1981 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - "Sonnet for a New Mother", 1981 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "For Our New Rector, Ash Wednesday, 1981", 1981-1996 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - "Reflections, Near a Boston School", 1981 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - "Abandoned Grocery Carts", 1981 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "Autumn Anniversary", 1981 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Thinking of a Friend, During City Walks", 1981 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - "The Fourth of July in Detroit, 1981" (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - "Labor Day, Dusk", 1982 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - "Visiting Old Teachers", 1984 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - "On Leaving the Church (1982)", 1984-1997 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - "Love Poison (USA, 1980, 58 min.)", 1988 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "Birdwatching Without Binoculars", 1988 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Poetry from the 1990s, 1990-2007; 3.
    This subseries contains drafts of poetry, along with poetry advertisements. Some of the dates range to years outside of the 90s due to the author's later revision of the poems. These drafts, referred to by the author as "discarded materials," are unpublished.
    - Poetry readings advertisements, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - "Lost and Found in Translation", 1990 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - "The Max Method, For Our 17th Anniversary", 1992 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - "Final Arrangements", 1992-1996 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - "Finding the Megathermiums", 1992-2007 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - "Yeats, My Sister, and The Giant Roving Ant", 1993 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - "A Diptych on Married Love", 1993 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - "Imagining our Apocalypse", 1993-1995 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - "The Way to See the World", 1993-1997 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - "Night Music", 1993 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - "Cataracts", 1993 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - "Notes from the Underground", 1994 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - "All Creatures Small", 1994 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - "Report from Bosnia", 1994-2002 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - "Illinois Exhibit, 1964", 1994 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - "Triplets", 1994 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - "Scanning the Rooflines, I see a Cat Fall in a Chimney and Disappear", 1994 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - "Glove/Dark Matter", 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - "After the Flood", 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - "Paul Wittgenstein Plays Ravel", 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - "Dog School at the Chinese Restaurant", 1995 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - "Meditations for a Young Dancer/Mary Hall", 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - "My Talk with Mr. Hamilton", 1996 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - "The Thieves", 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - "Personal Effects", 1996 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - "Corrective for a Friend's Wedding", 1996 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - "Self-Portrait at 45", 1995 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - "Reading Dante at the Ross Park Mall", 1993-1997 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - "Blake's Paramour", 1997 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - "For My Mother, Hale and Well, on Her 75th Birthday", 1997 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - "Sojourn in the City of Absence", 1998 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - "Birds, Saints, Weddings, Trees", 1998 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - "Dear Heart", 1999 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - "For a University Architect, at Fifty", 1999 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - "Where the Eggs are Kept", 1999 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - "A Wedding Toast", 1998 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Poetry from the 2000s, 2000-2020; 5.
    This subseries contains poetry drafts and email correspondences during the 2000s. Additionally, St. John's writing planner and poetry reading advertisements from this decade can also be found within the subseries. Some of the dates range to years outside of the 2000s due to the author's later revision of the poems. Oversized materials that appear in this series can be found in Oversize 5. These drafts, referred to by the author as "discarded materials," are unpublished.
    - Writing calendar, booklet/planner, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - "Encounters/Large Poem Explorations", 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Assorted poetry reading advertisements, 2000-2005 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Pittsburgh City Paper, "Notes from the Underground", 2001 (Oversize 5, Folder 2)
    - "Dolly Visits the Silver Eye Gallery", 2000 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - "Farewell, Abdul", 2000 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - "Another Morrow", 2001-2004 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - "Departures", 2001 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - "A Valedictorian Permitting Mourning", 2001 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Untitled drafts, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - "Weekend in Eden", 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - "Raccoons", 2002-2005 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - "The Deer at Wildwood", 2002 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - "Thirteen Ways of Looking at an Asteroid", 2002 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - "On the Bus", 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - "Tyke Poems", 2002 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - "Canto II", 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - "Canto I", 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - "Rainbow, March 26th", 2003 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - "Singing, On the Eve of War", 2003 (Box 3, Folder 77)